{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This settlement was abandoned after the loss of a trade network centered on Kilwa, leading its inhabitants to settle Mutapa. Sites at this settlement include the Great Enclosure and the Hill Complex, where eight birds carved of soapstone were once supposed to have stood. It was constructed by the Shona people, who protected themselves with high walls built without mortar. For ten points, name this Iron Age settlement that lends its name to an African country with capital Harare.",
      "answer": "Great Zimbabwe"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was not given songwriting credit on “Never Learn Not to Love” by the Beach Boys, even though it was derived from this man’s song “Cease to Exist.” This man’s belief in hidden messages on the Beatles’ White Album inspired the idea of a “Helter Skelter” race war. One of the stars of Valley of the Dolls, Sharon Tate, was over eight months pregnant when this man’s followers murdered her in 1969. For ten points, name this cult leader who died in prison in 2017.",
      "answer": "Charles Manson"
    },
    {
      "question": "A treaty with this name included the secret Act of Seclusion, by which the future William III lost the title of Stadtholder. The first and third Anglo-Dutch Wars were ended by treaties of this name. A 1931 statute of this name established protocols between the U.K. and dominion realms. A religious building with this name was built on the orders of Edward the Confessor and was the site of his burial. For ten points, give the name shared by the abbey where British monarchs are coronated.",
      "answer": [
        "Westminster",
        "Treaty of Westminster",
        "Statute of Westminster",
        "Westminster Abbey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these ships was deemed too slow for the Pacific Theatre and was used in Operation Leader in Norway. During Operation Torch, one of these ships supported ground troops and was named Ranger. In order to prevent the capture of Port Moresby by Japan, two of these ships were sent to the Coral Sea, leading to the scuttling of one called the Lexington. These ships were not present during the attack on Pearl Harbor. The Yorktown was, for ten points, what type of ship that provides a runway for warplanes?",
      "answer": "aircraft carriers"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man publicly debated Michel Foucault [foo-koh] in a TV program titled Human Nature: Justice versus Power. This man defended the right of a Holocaust denier to publish in the Faurisson affair. This thinker, who worked with Edward Herman on a book critical of the Vietnam War, coined the nonsense phrase “colorless green ideas sleep furiously” to illustrate the difference between grammar and syntax. For ten points, name this outspoken MIT professor, often considered the father of modern linguistics.",
      "answer": "Avram Noam Chomsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving this state, Matthew Lyon spat tobacco juice and defended himself with fireplace tongs during a 1798 incident with Roger Griswold in the House of Representatives. Seth Warner served as a captain in a militia sometimes called the Bennington Mob, named for a city in this state. Benning Wentworth made a series of land grants, including the town of Burlington, in, for ten points, what 14th US State where, in 1825, the Marquis de Lafayette toured Montpelier?",
      "answer": "Vermont"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was placed under house arrest after an outpouring of grief on Tomb-Sweeping Day; that came during a period of turmoil in which this man’s son was thrown out of a fourth-story window. This man, who succeeded the proponent of the “Two Whatevers,” Hua Guofeng [hwa gwo-fun], established Special Economic Zones as part of a philosophy that he summarized as “It doesn’t matter whether a cat is white or black, as long as it catches mice.” For ten points, name this “paramount leader” of China from 1978 to 1992 who began the country’s market reforms.",
      "answer": "Deng Xiaoping"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s brother killed Spencer Pettis after Pettis criticized this man’s work. Louis McLane was reassigned to the State Department for refusing to remove funds from an organization run by this man. After Langdon Cheves resigned, James Monroe replaced him with this man. In a political cartoon, this man is shown wearing a top hat as part of a many-headed monster being slain by the seventh President of the United States. Andrew Jackson was challenged by, for ten points, what final president of the Second Bank of the United States?",
      "answer": "Nicholas Biddle"
    },
    {
      "question": "A statue in this building allegedly features the face of an enemy general carved on the back of its head. This building’s 36 columns are accompanied by 48 stone festoons to indicate the growing number of states. Henry Bacon designed this building in the likeness of a Greek Doric temple, and Daniel Chester French designed a seated marble sculpture inside. Martin Luther King gave his “I Have a Dream” speech on the steps of, for ten points, what building that honors the 16th US President?",
      "answer": "Lincoln Memorial"
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving as consul, a man of this name oversaw the debate over the Oppian Law restricting the amount of wealth a woman could own, as well as two Porcian Laws protecting citizens from severe punishment. A man with this name opposed Julius Caesar and once forced him to choose a consulship over a triumph. The elder statesman of this name got his wish in the Third Punic War when Scipio Africanus razed a city that legendarily had salt sowed in its soil. For ten points, give this name shared by a censor of Rome who repeated at the end of his speeches, “Carthage must be destroyed.”",
      "answer": [
        "Cato",
        "Cato the Younger",
        "Cato the Elder"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist included a depiction of Sappho holding a scroll with her name on it, as well as Dante, Boccacio, and the nine muses in a depiction of Mount Parnassus. This artist, who began his career under Perugino, included a self-portrait as the Greek painter Apelles in one of his four frescoes for the Stanza della Segnatura, commissioned by Pope Julius II. For ten points, name this Italian painter who painted Plato and Aristotle conversing in his The School of Athens.",
        "answer": [
          "Raphael",
          "either",
          "both underlined parts of Raffaello Sanzio da Urbino"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Raphael’s School of Athens also includes a portrait of this architect, the planner of St. Peter’s Basilica, using a compass.",
        "answer": "Donato Bramante"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, General Claudius Easley was shot by a sniper while General Simon Bolivar Buckner Jr. was killed from flying coral after an artillery attack. Shuri Castle and Sugar Loaf Hill were strongly defended positions in this battle. In a phase of this battle called Operation Ten-Go, the battleship Yamato was destroyed. This battle was supposed to allow U.S. forces to invade the Japanese mainland. For ten points, name final island-hopping battle that followed Iwo Jima on one of the Ryukyu Islands in 1945.",
        "answer": "Battle of Okinawa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This war correspondent, who won the 1944 Pulitzer Prize for telling the stories of American troops, was killed by a sniper during the Battle of Okinawa on the island of Iejima.",
        "answer": "Ernest “Ernie” Pyle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician’s attempt in mid-2017 to suppress the Maute [mao-tay] group led to a protracted siege of the city of Marawi. This man, who chaired the most recent ASEAN summit, attracted controversy in 2016 for comments surrounding the rape of the Australian missionary Jacqueline Hamill. Time Magazine labeled this man as “The Punisher” in response to his use of extrajudicial “death squads” against drug dealers. For ten points, name this current president of the Philippines.",
        "answer": "Rodrigo Roa Duterte"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to serving as President, Duterte [doo-tare-tay] served as mayor of this Philippine city.",
        "answer": "Davao City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object is displayed prominently on the Mykonos Vase. A story about this object relates how Anticlus was tempted to call out to his wife when a woman impersonated her voice. Epeius supervised the construction of this object, which was presented by Sinon as an offering to Athena from an army that had abandoned their cause. Odysseus and forty of his warriors hid inside, for ten points, what wooden animal that was dragged inside the walls of Troy?",
        "answer": "Trojan Horse"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This male prophet’s calls to “Beware of Greeks bearing gifts” was ignored by the Trojans prior to accepting the horse. In most traditions, this man was killed along with his two sons by sea serpents.",
        "answer": "Laocoon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "AscandalinvolvingillegalshipmentsofarmstothiscountryinvolvedCharlesPasqua,Jean-Christophe Mitterand, and several French writers and artists. The Bicesse Accord set up a plan for democracy in this country with the support of President Jos´e Eduardo dos Santos. In 1992, fighting in this country intensified in the Halloween Massacre between the ruling party once backed by Cuban military aid, the MPLA, and the opposition UNITA party. For ten points, name this former Portuguese colony that is governed from Luanda.",
        "answer": "Angola"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Angolan Civil War, the FLEC groups fought for the independence of this Angolan exclave, which is separated from Angola by a strip of DRC territory.",
        "answer": "Cabinda Province"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This invention is believed to have been first created by the Swedish army officer D.H. Fridberg, who produced the “Kjellman” [k’yell-man] version. Later versions of this device were manufactured by Hotchkiss and Vickers. Hiram Maxim perfected the first practical form of this weapon, which was used to sustained, deadly effect in No Man’s Land during World War I. John Browning also designed, for ten points, what fully automatic weapons that often use a belt feeder and a bipod stand?",
        "answer": "machine gun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During World War I, this German airplane manufacturer invented the gun synchronizer to prevent machine guns mounted on fighters from firing bullets into the propellers.",
        "answer": [
          "Fokker Aviatik GmBH",
          "Fokker Flugzeugwerke GmbH",
          "Fokker Werke GmbH",
          "Fokker Aeroplanbau"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1917, this state’s governor, Frank Lowden, sent National Guardsmen to stop a race riot, but most Guardsmen refused to help while police joined the fighting; a 1917 Silent Protest Parade in New York City was a direct response to that riot in this state. The arrest of two black men in this state’s capital sparked a 1908 race riot that led to the creation of the NAACP. For ten points, name this state where mass lynchings took place in East St. Louis and Springfield.",
        "answer": "Illinois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some reports claim that this man took part in the 1919 Chicago race riot as a teenager, four decades before he was elected mayor and five decades before he used so-called “Gestapo tactics” in the streets of Chicago.",
        "answer": "Richard Joseph Daley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A civil war of these people resulted in John of Giscala massacring Ananus’ followers. To win a battle against these people, government forces rolled a siege tower up a dirt ramp to avoid traversing the well-defended “snake road.” Shortly after he was victorious at the siege of Yodfat, Vespasian hired one of these people, Josephus, as his biographer. A faction of these people committed mass suicide atop Masada fortress rather than surrender, leading them to be known as the Zealots. For ten points, name this religious group that tried to expel the Romans from Jerusalem.",
        "answer": [
          "Jewish people",
          "Zealots before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This emperor’s capture of Jerusalem was celebrated in an arch erected by his brother Domitian. Despite his campaigns, this emperor would later cause controversy by marrying a Jewish queen, Berenice.",
        "answer": [
          "Titus",
          "Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus, but do not"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Alaska",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colonial power that ruled Alaska before selling it to the United States.",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 19th century event that brought an influx of immigrants into Alaska, begun by a discovery by Soapy Smith.",
          "answer": "Klondike Gold Rush or Yukon Gold Rush"
        },
        {
          "question": "US Secretary of State who purchased Alaska for 7.2 million dollars.",
          "answer": [
            "William Seward",
            "Seward’s Folly"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alaska governor who was nominated for the Vice Presidency in 2008.",
          "answer": "Sarah Palin"
        },
        {
          "question": "British navigator who visited Alaska as part of a series of voyages aboard the Endeavor.",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "plane crash.",
          "answer": "Ted Stevens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial capital of Alaska, the site of an 1804 battle against the Tlingit.",
          "answer": "Sitka"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two Aleutian islands that were occupied by Japan during World War II.",
          "answer": "Attu and/or Kiska"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Greek Combat",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Long race named in honor of a 490 BC Greek victory over Persia.",
          "answer": [
            "Marathon",
            "Battle of Marathon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek kingdom ruled by the conquerors Alexander the Great and his father, Philip II.",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military formation of troops and hoplites armed with spears and shields, the basic infantry unit in ancient Greece.",
          "answer": "phalanx"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of victory in which the winning side endures unsustainable casualties, named after an ancient commander who won at Asculum and Heraclea.",
          "answer": [
            "Pyrrhic Victory",
            "Pyrrhus of Epirus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of galley that formed the bulk of the Athenian navy, named for its three rows of oars.",
          "answer": "trireme"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek city state whose army, including the Sacred Band, executed one of the first flanking maneuvers over Sparta at the Battle of Leuctra [look-tra].",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander who won the battles of Leuctra and Mantinea [man-ti-nay-uh].",
          "answer": "Epaminondas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long, pike-like spear introduced by Philip II to replace the dory in his armies.",
          "answer": "sarissa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial India",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country whose Indian territories were annexed after the Seven Years War; its East India Company was founded by Jean-Baptiste Colbert",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonviolent leader who protested British rule with a salt march to Dandi.",
          "answer": "Mohandas Gandhi or Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region where the British conquest of India began; the region around its namesake bay is divided between India and Bangladesh",
          "answer": [
            "Bengal",
            "Bay of Bengal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1857 mutiny of native Indian soldiers that ended company rule in India.",
          "answer": "Sepoy Mutiny or Uprising, Revolt, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "1756 incident in which several British East India Company employees died in a crowded prison cell.",
          "answer": "Black Hole of Calcutta"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Reginald Dyer’s men fired into a crowd of pilgrims in 1919, killing hundreds.",
          "answer": "Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rocket-loving Indian state ruled by Tipu Sultan and conquered by the British in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Mysore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Doctrine that allowed Britain to take control of princely states whose rulers had no male heir.",
          "answer": "Doctrine of Lapse"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, Wesley Everest was lynched after the IWW and the American Legion clashed in the town of Centralia. Protesters in this state made pamphlets encouraging revolution with phrase “Russia Did It” during a 1919 general strike that was remarkably peaceful, yet put down with troops by Mayor Ole (20 pts)",
        "Hanson. This state is home to the Hanford Works site, which was part of the Manhattan Project. During the Great Depression, workers built the (10 pts)",
        "Grand Coulee Dam on the Columbia River in, for ten points, what Pacific Northwest state where Boeing built World War II bombers in Seattle?"
      ],
      "answer": "Washington"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A device that relies on this effect called an h/e apparatus can be used to experimentally determine Planck’s constant. This effect was discovered after an observation that illumination with UV light made electrodes produce (20 pts)",
        "sparks more easily. As the theories of relativity were still controversial in 1921, the Nobel committee emphasized the discovery of this effect in (10 pts)",
        "Albert Einstein’s citation. For ten points, name this effect in which high-energy photons dislodge electrons from a metal."
      ],
      "answer": "photoelectric effect"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s brief, post-war second term as mayor ended when Gerald Templer fired him for “laziness and incompetence.” This politician aimed to pull the Zentrum “out of the tower” by uniting Protestants and Catholics in one party. The Miracle on the (20 pts)",
        "Rhine was caused by this man’s finance minister, Ludwig Erhard. This leader, who defeated rival Kurt Schumacher in a 1949 election, controversially suggested that (10 pts)",
        "Bonn, not Frankfurt, be made his provisional capital. For ten points, name this founder of the Christian Democratic Union, the first Chancellor of West Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Konrad Adenauer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the aftermath of this battle, one side established the Stanley Internment Camp and brutally tortured Mateen Ansari. St. Stephen’s College, a makeshift hospital, was the site of a massacre during this battle in which wounded soldiers were (20 pts)",
        "bayoneted in their beds. After 17 days of fighting, this battle ended when Governor Mark (10 pts)",
        "Young personally surrendered on “Black Christmas.” For ten points, name this 1941 battle in which Japanese forces captured a British city on the Pearl River."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hong Kong",
        "Xianggang baowei zhan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country arrested hundreds of “Swing Kids,” who preferred English language music. The opera Jonny Strikes Up by Ernst Krenek was criticized in a music exhibition in this country, which commissioned (20 pts)",
        "Carl Orff to write incidental music for Shakespeare’s Midsummer Night’s Dream to replace Felix (10 pts)",
        "Mendelssohn’s work. Jazz and twelve-tone music were banned as “degenerate music” by, for ten points, what country from which Arnold Schoenberg and other Jewish composers fled in the 1930s?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. An intervention in a war between these two countries was the subject of the Simla Manifesto, promising to restore Shah Shuja. Louis Cavagnari served as a diplomat from one of these two countries to the other but was killed in riots after the 1879 Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Gandamak paused a war between these two countries; after those riots, Abdur Rahman Khan was installed as Emir. One of these countries imposed the (10 pts)",
        "Durand Line on the other as its border with modern Pakistan. For ten points, name these two countries that fought three wars in the 19th and 20th centuries, the last of which ended with a European power vacating Kabul."
      ],
      "answer": "Emirate of Afghanistan and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote about a young couple who commit suicide after the failure of an uprising in late February in his story “Patriotism.” This author’s death (20 pts)",
        "poem, which declares that “failing is the essence of a flower,” was composed in preparation for his takeover of an army outpost. (10 pts)",
        "The Temple of the Golden Pavilion was written by, for ten points, what Japanese author who completed his The Sea of Fertility series before his ritual suicide, or seppuku, after the failure of an imperialist coup in 1970?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yukio Mishima or Kimitake Hiraoka",
        "names in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Calef denounced this event in a work that contains the controversial “Narrative of a Visit.” John Alden escaped this event but returned after “the public had regained its use of (20 pts)",
        "reason.” William Phips created a Court of Oyer and Terminer headed by William Stoughton during this event. (10 pts)",
        "Cotton Mather defended his role in this event in his Wonders of the Invisible World. For ten points, name this 1692 to 1693 bit of mass hysteria in Massachusetts during which numerous girls were executed for allegedly using magic."
      ],
      "answer": "Salem Witch Trials"
    }
  ]
}